Emily Wall

My research involves decision making using data visualization and visual analytics. I develop computational strategies to characterize human limitations in decision making (e.g., cognitive bias) and design interventions to promote reflective data analysis and decision making processes.

I will be joining the Department of Computer Science at Emory University as an Assistant Professor in Fall 2021. I am currently completing a Postdoc at Northwestern University with Jessica Hullman and Steve Franconeri (Summer 2020 - Summer 2021). I completed my Ph.D. in Computer Science at Georgia Tech in 2020.

emily.wall@emory.edu

Google Scholar

emilywall.github.io

in LinkedIn

y @embwall

PDF of CV

Appointments

2021- Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science

Emory University

2020-2021 Postdoctoral Researcher

Department of Computer Science

Northwestern University

Education

2020 Ph.D. in Computer Science

Georgia Institute of Technology

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Committee: Alex Endert, John Stasko, Polo Chau, Brian Fisher, Wenwen Dou

2015 B.S. in Computer Science & Mathematics

University of Georgia summa cum laude

Honors & Awards

2020	VGTC Best Dissertation, Honorable Mention
2019	GVU Foley Scholar, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology
2019	D.E. Shaw Exploration Fellowship, Recipient
2019	Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship, Recipient

2018	GVU Foley Scholar, Finalist, Georgia Institute of Technology
2017	Graduate Student Symposium, Participant, AT&T Labs
2017	Doctoral Colloquium, Participant, IEEE VIS
2017-2020	Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD), Recipient
2017	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program, Honorable Mention
2017	Department of Defense SMART Fellowship, Recipient (Declined)
2015-2019	President's Fellowship, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology
2015	CURO Symposium Best Paper Award, University of Georgia
2014	CURO Research Assistantship, University of Georgia
2014	Hahn Family Scholarship for Computer Science, Recipient, University of Georgia
2013	Hollingsworth Award for Excellence in Mathematics, Recipient, University of
	Georgia
2012-2015	Zell Miller Scholarship, Recipient, University of Georgia

Publications

Journal Articles

A Heuristic Approach to Value-Driven Evaluation of Visualizations

E. Wall, M. Agnihotri, L. Matzen, K. Divis, M. Haass, A. Endert, and J. Stasko IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. InfoVis'18), 2019.

🖺 PDF | 🖽 Talk | 🏶 Website | 🕪 Video FF

Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics

E. Wall, S. Das, R. Chawla, B. Kalidindi, E. Brown, and A. Endert

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'17), 2018.

 PDF | 目 Talk | ▶ Video | ▶ Video FF | □ Demo

AxiSketcher: Interactive Nonlinear Axis Mapping of Visualizations through User Drawings

B.C. Kwon, H. Kim, E. Wall, J. Choo, H. Park, and A. Endert

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'16), 2017.

PDF | ► Video

Conference Proceedings

Toward a Design Space for Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Vis

E. Wall, J. Stasko, and A. Endert

IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers, 2019.

🖺 PDF | 🖿 Supplemental | 🖽 Talk | 🛏 Video FF

A Markov Model of Users' Interactive Behavior in Scatterplots

E. Wall, A. Arcalgud, K. Gupta, and A. Jo

IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers, 2019.

PDF | ⊞ Talk | Nideo FF

A Formative Study of Interactive Bias Metrics in Visual Analytics Using Anchoring Bias

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, and A. Endert

Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19), 2019.

PDF | ► Video

Using Expert Patterns in Assisted Interactive Machine Learning: A Study in Machine Teaching

E. Wall, S. Ghorashi, and G. Ramos

Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19), 2019.

PDF | ► Video

Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, L. Franklin, and A. Endert

IEEE Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST), 2017.

 PDF | I Talk | I Video | I Video FF

Supporting Team-First Visual Analytics through Group Activity Representations

S.K. Badam, Z. Zeng, *E. Wall*, A. Endert, and N. Elmqvist *Graphics Interface*, 2017.

PDF | ► Video

Workshop Papers

COVID-19 Health Equity Dashboard - Addressing Vulnerable Populations

S. Liu, *E. Wall*, S. Patel, and Y. Park

Visualization for Communication (VisComm, at VIS'20), 2020.

₽DF

Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

DECISIVe: Workshop on Dealing with Cognitive Biases in Visualizations (at InfoVis'17), 2017.

PDF

Book Chapters

Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

Cognitive Biases in Visualizations, Ed. G. Ellis, Springer, 2018, Chapter 3, pp. 29-42.

■ Book | **■** Chapter

Theses

Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Emily Wall

Georgia Tech, School of Interactive Computing Ph.D. Thesis. April 2020.



Professional Experience

2015-2020 Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Graduate Research Assistant Advised by Dr. Alex Endert

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Summer 2018 Microsoft Research, Seattle, WA

Intern, Machine Teaching Group Mentored by Dr. Gonzalo Ramos

Modeled how experts use machine teaching to train ML classifiers. Developed systematic guidelines to help novices train ML classifiers.

Summer 2016 Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, Richland, WA

Intern, Visual Analytics Group

Mentored by Lyndsey Franklin and Kris Cook

Developed heuristics to characterize bias in real-time from user interaction sequences

2013-2015 Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA

Intern, Systems Engineering Group

Advised by Marc Sarrel

 ${\sf Used \; SysML \; and \; principles \; of \; Model-Based \; Systems \; Engineering \; to \; visualize \; network}$

flows for Lockheed Martin's Orion capsule

Fall 2014 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Don Potter

Developed neural network to predict solar radiation in Georgia; funded by the Georgia

Power Advanced Solar Initiative

Fall 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Liming Cai

Used sequence alignment techniques to determine coevolution of species with a

common ancestor

Spring 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Prashant Doshi

Created simulation and programmable interface for Parrot A.R. Drone quadcopters to

serve as a testbed for autonomous decision making with UAVs

Grants & Funding

2019-2020 Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision Making with Visual

Analytics

Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship

Co-Pls: <u>Dr. Alex Endert</u> Funded: \$101,435

2019 Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

GVU Foley Scholar
Co-Pls: Dr. Alex Endert

Funded: \$5,000

2017-2020 Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision-Making With Visual

Analytics

Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD)

Co-PIs: Dr. Alex Endert

Funded: \$20,000 / year for 3 years

2014 Predicting Solar Radiation in Georgia

CURO Research Assistantship

Co-Pls: <u>Dr. Don Potter</u> Funded: \$1,000

Teaching

Teaching Assistant

Spring 2019 Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460) (133 students)

Georgia Institute of Technology

Fall 2017 Information Visualization (CS 7450) (74 students)

Georgia Institute of Technology

Fall 2013 Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301)

University of Georgia

Fall 2012 Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301)

University of Georgia

Guest Lectures

Feb 2019 Introduction to Javascript

Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of Technology

Dec 2017 Cognition in Visualization

Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology

Nov 2017 **Visual Analytics**

Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology

Jun 2017 Visualization Design: Do's and Don'ts

Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of Technology

Presentations

Invited Talks

As We Are: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

> October 2020. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. Virtual Brown Bag.

- > September 2020. Emory University. Atlanta, GA. 🛂 Abstract
- > May 2020. CMU & AFRL, Center for Excellence on Human-Machine Teaming, Virtual Brown Bag.
- > May 2020. Siemens. Virtual Brown Bag.
- > March 2020. Cornell University, Info Science Colloquium. Ithaca, NY. 🗗 Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Washington, Allen School Colloquium. Seattle, WA. 🔄 Watch
- > February 2020. Emory University. Atlanta, GA. 🗖 Abstract
- > February 2020. New York University. New York, NY. 🛂 Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Wisconsin. Madison, WI.

Left, Right, and Gender: Mitigating Implicit Human Bias in Visual Analytics

> January 2020. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Brown Bag. Atlanta, GA. 🗗 Watch

The Interactive Analytics Library: Treating Interaction as Data

> May 2017. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. Richland, WA.

Posters and Demonstrations

Warning, Bias May Occur: Detecting and Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > October 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > June 2019. Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality. Berlin, Germany.
- > April 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics (Demo)

- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Francisco, CA.
- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Diego, CA.
- > April 2016. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

Mentoring

2017

2020-2021	Jenni Hutson , B.A. Computer Science and Radio/TV/Film, Northwestern University, Class of 2021 Developed system for visualization recommendations that support decision making
2020	Star Liu, B.S. Quantitative Sciences, Emory University, Class of 2021 Developed system for visualizing health inequities during the COVID-19 pandemic, first author of case study on COVID-19 Health Equity Dashboard
2020	Jamal Paden, B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2020 Conducted usability testing for bias mitigation interventions
2017-2018	Yingxiao Ouyang , M.S. HCI, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2019 Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions Now: UX Designer at Walmart Labs

Qiaochu Mu, M.S. HCI, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018

Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions

2016-2017 Bharath Kalidindi, B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018

Developed system for ranking data from user interaction, coauthored publication of

Podium

Now: Software Engineer at Yahoo

Service

Professional Service

> Program Committee Member

IEEE VIS Short Papers, 2020

VISxAl Workshop at IEEE VIS, 2019

CHI Late Breaking Work, 2018

> Reviewer

IEEE VIS: 2017-2020 CHI: 2018-2020 TVCG: 2018-2020 EuroVis: 2020

International Journal of Human-Computer Studies: 2019

KDD IDEA: 2017 VAST Challenge: 2016

2020 Organizer

TRust and Expertise in Visual Analytics (TREX) Workshop at IEEE VIS

2017 Panelist

Advancing Visualization Inclusion and Diversity (AVID) Workshop at IEEE VIS

Institutional Service

2018-2020 Graduate Student Council Chair, School of Interactive Computing

Representative of graduate students in the School of Interactive Computing

2017-2018 Graduate Student Council Travel Committee

Responsible for reviewing and awarding travel grants to graduate student applicants

in the College of Computing

Selected Media

Nov 2019 A Reflection on VIS2019: Or, How Doomed Are We? Medium Blog Post, Multiple

Views on Visualization Research Explained.

by Michael Correll

Nov 2019 Highlights from IEEE VIS 2019, Uncharted Software Blog. ■ Read

by Rosa Romero-Gómez

May 2019 Battling Bias. Ep. 3, Tech Unbound Podcast. • Listen

with Josh Preston

Other Professional Activities

Oct 2019 NextProf Nexus Workshop
Atlanta, GA

Jun 2019 Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality
Berlin, Germany

Apr 2018 CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop
San Francisco, CA

Oct 2016 Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing
Houston, TX

Apr 2016 CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop
San Diego, CA